A Guide to the Jacques Loeb papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA176
Rockefeller Archive Center
Jacques Loeb papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1908-1924
Rockefeller Archive Center
Loeb, Jacques
FA176
2 Cubic Feet 2 boxes and 10 volumes
2 boxes including volume of Osterhout article; 9 volumes
Approximately 1 cubic foot.
Biographical/Historical note
Jacques Loeb (1859-1924) physician and physiologist, Member of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, director of Experimental Biology from 1910 until his death in 1924.
Member and Honorary Member of numerous Societies.
Biographical note
1859 Born April 7, Mayen, Germany
1877-1880 Graduate Askanisches Gymnasium, Berlin
1884 M.D. University of Strasbourg
1885 Staatsexamen
1885-1886 Ph. D, Sc. D. University of Berlin
1886-1888 Assistant in Physiology, University of Würzburg
1888-1890 Assistant in Physiology, University of Strasbourg
1889-1891 Biological Station, Naples
1891-1892 Associate in Biology, Bryn Mawr College
1892-1895 Associate Professor in physiology and Experimental Biology University of Chicago
1895-1900 Associate Professor in physiology, University of Chicago
1900-1902 Professor in physiology, University of Chicago
1902-1910 Professor of physiology, University of California
1909 Honorary D. Sc, Cambridge, Eng.; Honorary M.D., Geneva; Honorary Ph. D., Leipzig
1910- Member, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York
1924 Died February 11, Bermuda
Scope and Contents note
Administrative correspondence, biographical articles, photographs, bibliography, and collected reprints.
Arrangement note
Correspondence arranged in chronological order.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 L823
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Medical sciences; Medical research; Physiology; Life sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Bibliography of the Published Writings of Jacques Loeb, compiled by Nina Kobelt. Typescript and printed copy, 1924 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Printed obituaries and biographical memoirs, 1924-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes Russian translation of W.J.V. Osterhout's memoir.
- Program for unveiling of memorial tablet, Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole, Massachusetts, 1927 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Jacques Loeb Memorial Supplement" The Collecting Net, 1928 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Academic appointments held...", circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photocopies of obituaries for Mrs. Loeb (d. 20 August 1951) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Portraits: by Louis Schmidt (multiple copies) no neg. in folder, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Includes drawing from photograph.
- Portraits: Undated, standing, with hands in pockets. 2 copies, plus enlargement of head. No neg. in folder (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Portraits: by Louis Schmidt. Multiple copies, no neg. in folder, circa 1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Informal snapshots, many taken at Woods Hole, most undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous photos, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes 2 photos of Leo Loeb, one dated 1921; print of Jacques Loeb Memorial Tablet [Woods Hole], 1928.
- Correspondence, 1906 1909-1910
  Arrangement
  Arranged in chronologically.
  - Loeb/Simon Flexner, 13 (?) Jun 1906, re possible position for Prof. H. Borrattass of Göttingen, a "first class man" in nerve physiology and pathology; Flexner/Loeb 27 Jul 1906, reply (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Flexner/Loeb, 12 Oct 1909, re possibility of Loeb coming to the Rockefeller Institute; Loeb/Flexner, 14 Oct 1909, will seriously consider offer, 1909 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re "call to Europe", 1909 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hermann M. Biggs/Flexner, re Loeb, 1909 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Flexner/Theobald Smith, 20 Nov 1909, re Loeb; Smith/Flexner, 23 Nov 1909, reply, 1909 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Flexner/Loeb, "delighted" Loeb will be able to come to New York for conference, 1909 November 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loeb/Flexner [Hotel Belmont, NY stationery], thanks for Flexner's kindness; requests Flexner obtain information about sources of material, from New York Aquarium or possibly "Morgan, Wilson, or Davenport." Flexner/Loeb, 22 Dec 1909, reply, 1909 December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loeb/Flexner, telegram: "letter received offer Generous shall probably accept letter follows", [1909] December 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loeb/Flexner, thanks for offer, would accept "at once if it was not for Budapest", 1909 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Flexner/Loeb, writing on behalf of Executive Committee of the Rock. Inst, re appointment. Typed copy marked "Not sent", 1909 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loeb/Flexner, telegram: "Accept with thanks offer of headship of department of Experimental biology Rockefeller Institute", 1910 January 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re possible visit to Plymouth, England to study methods of raising marine larvae, 1910 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, returned from Pacific Grove where he has been working on tissue extracts; postscript re Budapest, 1910 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, psychiatrist Adolph Meyer is "pleased" with Loeb's decision; has begun to raise fungi on cow dung "which I am sure can be had in the neighborhood of New York", 1910 January 19 (?) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Flexner/Loeb, has received a note from Davenport re sea-urchins at Cold Spring Harbor, 1910 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re Hardolph Wasteneys, 1910 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, needs more space at Woods Hole; Loeb would like to work at the Fish Commission "if it were not that my friends at the MBL [Marine Biological Laboratory] might take offence at it..". Flexner/Loeb, 22 Mar 1910, reply, 1910 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, enclosing list of apparatus. Flexner will "feel gratified to see, that I intend having 2 kymographs. I am not as bad as my reputation - I may even vivisect", 1910 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, enclosing chemical list. "It is very important for any work to have the purest chemicals obtainable in the market", 1910 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, Wasteneys will be arriving in New York to prepare Loeb's solutions and apparatus for Woods Hole, 1910 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/[James] Norris, request for blood serum. "There is no slaughter house here or in the vicinity...", 1910 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, possibility of invitation to Dr. [Otto] Warburg, who "has published a series of very brilliant papers concerning the oxydations in the animal cell...", 1911 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re fellowship for Dr. Wolfgang Ewald, 1912 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Loeb/Jerome D. Greene, re possibility of grant to Professor Bechhold of Dr. Ehrlich's laboratory, to equip Department of Colloidal Chemistry; Greene/ Loeb, 29 Apr-1912, re Rock. Found, 1912 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Loeb/Greene, 3 May 1912, re foundation of an International Institute for the Investigation of the Effects of Alcohol; Greene/Loeb, 7 May 1912, re Rock. Found, 1912 May (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Greene/Loeb, re Edward Forbes at Woods Hole, 1912 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Loeb/Greene, report of work with Dr. Beutner, 1912 June 17 1912 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Report of the Department of Experimental Biology," typescript, circa July 1912; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re Frank Bancroft's return to California, 1913 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Loeb/[Kornel] v. Körösy, re possibility of v. Körösy working with Loeb on tropisms, 1913 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [Henry James Jr.] /Loeb, re room at Woods Hole for Dr. [Edward] Uhlenhut, 1914 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re appointment of McKeen Cattell as summer assistant, 1915 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Loeb/James, quotes telegram L. sent to President [Woodrow] Wilson, 1915 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Loeb/James, re work of Madame [Danchakoff], 1915 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - James/Loeb, requests scientific report "intelligible" to the Board of Trustees, 1915 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - James/Loeb, re [John] Northrop, 1915 October 25 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - James/Loeb, re appointment of Mary Andrews, 1916 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Loeb/Edric B. Smith, re death of frogs, 1916 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James/Loeb, requests scientific report for Board of Trustees, 1916 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Loeb/James, needs place to raise flies for feeding of frogs, 1916 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James/Loeb, appointment of Dr. [Florence H]. Francis; re Dr. Raymond Pearl, 1916 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Loeb/James, comments on war, 1917 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James/Loeb, re appointment of Dr. Carl B. Dermby, 1917 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Loeb/James, re Mr. [Moses] Kunitz, 1918 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re American Journal of Physiology, 1919 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Loeb/Flexner, 14 Apr 1919 re proposed budget, 1919-1920 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ph. Rummel/J.P. Warbasse, 8 Jun 1919 and 7 Nov 1919, re Loeb and Socialism (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Loeb/Edric B. Smith, re Miss Helen McNaught, 1920 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Loeb/Flexner, 1 and 11 Dec 1919, re B.M. Allen; Allen/Loeb, [1919] (copy) Loeb/Flexner, 25 Jan 1921, re change in division's name from "Experimental Biology" to "General Physiology" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re Miss [Elizabeth] Brakeley and importance of maintaining good relations with chemical laboratory at Columbia [University], 1921 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - A.J. Gelarie/Loeb, letter of complaint, 1914 August 25 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Loeb/James, (copy) re Gelarie, 1914 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re letter from [Frank R.] Lillie, 1921 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Smith/Loeb, re appointment of David Hitchcock, 1921 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Loeb/Flexner, request for helper to prepare protein solutions, 1922 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - F. Foerster/Loeb, (translation and copy), re Loeb consent to give address at meeting of Bunsen Association in Leipsic, 1922 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Loeb/Flexner, decision not to go abroad because 1) wife's poor health and 2) Wilhelm Ostwald and [Walther] Nernst are other speakers on program and Loeb's attendance "would have pained the French and Belgian scientists", 1922 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Loeb/Flexner, re 1) visit of Ivan P. Pavlov and son at Woods Hole; 2) discussion with Pavlov about P. Lasareff; 3) receipt of letter from Prof. O. Warburg re [Otto] Meyerhof and anti-Semitism; Flexner/Loeb, 5 Jul 1923, reply, 1923 June 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - P. Lasareff/Loeb, (copy), re proposed trip to American; paragraph on "big geophysical work on the investigation of the Kursk magnetic anomaly", 1923 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Richard Lorenz/Loeb, (in German), re Loeb's theory and Lorenz's own work on strong electrolytes, 1923 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Loeb/Flexner, recommends visits of P. Lasareff, Otto Warburg, and Richard Lorenz, 1923 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - B.A. Younker/Loeb, attorney on behalf of A.J. Gelarie, 1924 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - A. Einstein/Loeb, (copy and translation), re possibility of support from Rockefeller Institute for theoretical assistant for work on general relativity; pleased to hear of R.I. support of O. Warburg; brief comments on situation in Europe. [2 p. listing of Contents of Albert Einstein file, International Education Board Archives], 1923 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Selected condolence letters (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - J. Stanley Gardiner, 1924 February 15
    - [Adolph] Von Harnack, 1924 February 16
    - Baron D.S. Kitasato, 1924 February 18
    - E. Rutherford, 1924 February 18
    - Otto Meyerhof, 1924 February 19
    - A. Einstein, (copy), 1924 February 19
    - Otto Meyerhof, (copy), 1924 February 20
    - Leo Loeb, 1924 February 21
    - Hardolph Wasteneys, 1924 February 22
    - Rudolf Höber, 1924 February 23
    - Hans H. Meyer, 1924 February 28
    - M.F. Guyer, 1924 March 3
    - Curt Herbst, 1924 March 3
    - Et. Burnet, 1924 March 10
    - F.G. Donnan, (copy), 1924 March 15
    - Svante Arrhenius, (copy), 1924 March 16
    - O. Herzog, 1924 March 21
    - I.P. Pavlov, 1924 March 31
  - "Jacques Loeb" by John H. Northrop, carbon typescript, circa February 1924 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Prof. Rona, (extract and copy), condolence letter, 1924 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - E.P. Lyon, (copy), condolence letter, 1924 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Flexner/Mrs. Loeb, "Memorial Minute to Jacques Loeb", 1924 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Frank R. Lillie/Flexner, re Loeb memorial tablet for Marine Biological, 1926 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Laboratory, Woods Hole, photograph (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Thos. C. Corner/Flexner, re portrait of Dr. Loeb, 1930 June 11 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Robert F. Loeb/Herbert S. Gasser, telegram re death of Mrs. Jacques Loeb, 1951 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- File on Leo Loeb, 1906-1915
  - Flexner/ L. Loeb, re L. Loeb's "conflict with Dr. Gaylord."; L., 1907 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Loeb/Flexner, replies, 1907 October 25-26 1907 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - L. Loeb/Board of Trustees of the R.I.M.R., application for grant of $600 "to carry out certain investigations in the growth of tissues and allied problems and in the coagulation of the blood"; Flexner/Loeb, 14 Jan 1908, reply, 1908 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - L. Loeb/L. Emmett Holt, report of scientific work, 1908 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - L. Loeb/Board of Scientific Directors of the R.I.M.R., report of scientific work; Flexner/Loeb, 1 Dec 1909, reply, 1909 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence re reprints, 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Isaac A. Abt/ Flexner, re director for reorganized Michael Reese Hospital and the Morris Institute for Medical Research; Flexner/Abt, 21 Dec 1914, recommends Loeb, 1914 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Flexner-L. Loeb correspondence., re temporary transfer of L. Loeb's work to Institute; 1 letter, J. Loeb/Flexner, ca Dec 1914, re L. Loeb and position at Michael Reese Hospital, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Short Register, Jacques Loeb Papers, Library of Congress, Manuscript Division (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jacques Loeb/William J. Crozier, marked "Confidential" re founding of a Journal of General Physiology, 1918 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Also in folder: photocopy of letter and envelope from Mrs. Garn to Dr. Jules Hirsch.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Addition. Gift of Priscilla Crozier Garn. Transmitted to Archives via Mrs. Sonya W. Mirsky, 25 March 1986.
- Photocopy and clippings of articles in newspapers which appeared at the time of Dr. Loeb's death. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Magazine articles about Jacques Loeb
  - Stockbridge, Frank. "Creating Life in the Laboratory" Cosmopolitan Magazine 774-781, 1912 May (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Serviss, Garrett P. "Artificial Creation of Life" Cosmopolitan Magazine 459-468, 1905 September (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - De Kruif, Paul. "Jacques Loeb, the Mechanist" Harper Magazine 183-190 (2 cop), 1923 January (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Obituary Prof. Jacques Loeb Nature v. 113, 574-576, 1924 April 19 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Levene and Osterhout. Jacques Loeb, the Man and Jacques Loeb, the scientist. Science 59 (1924) 427-430 (2 cop) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Garrey, W.E. "Memorial to Jacques Loeb" Science 59 (1925) 198 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Honorary Degrees at Yale University" Science 57 (1923) 11 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Osterhout, W.J.V. "Jacques Loeb, Biographical Sketch" Journal of General Physiology 8 (1928) ix-xcii (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Jacques Loeb" JGP 6 (1924) unpaged (2 cop) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Memorial to Jacques Loeb" by Levene, Osterhout, Flexner, Lillie. Proceeding of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine 21 (1924) i-xiv (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Williams, H.S. "Our Twelve Great Scientists. IX. Dr. Jacques Loeb" Technical World Magazine 761-765, 1915 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Flexner, Simon, "Jacques Loeb and his Period" Science 66 (1927) 333-337 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Jacques Loeb" Medical News JAMA 82 (1924) 722, 563 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "Obituary: Jacques Loeb" Medical Journal and Record 267, 1924 March (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Herbst, Curt "Jacques Loeb; a short survey of his life-work" Die Naturwissenschaften the original in German with an English translation, 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Uhlenhuth, Eduard. "Jacques Loeb" The Nation 118 (1924) 229 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Gussin, Arnold E.S..: "Jacques Loeb: The Man and His Tropism Theory of Animal Conduct", Journal of the History of Medicine oct 1963, photocopy, 16 pp (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Collected reprints (v. 1-7), 7 volumes (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Loeb, Jacques. Proteins and the theory of colloidal behavior. New York, McGraw-Hill (v. 8), 1924; 1 volume (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Loeb, Jacques. Regeneration from a physico-chemical viewpoint. New York, McGraw-Hill (v. 9), 1924; 1 volume (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Loeb, Jacques. The mechanistic conception of life. Edited and with introduction by Donald Fleming, Cambridge, Mass. Belknap Press (v. 10), 1964; 1 volume (Box 2, Folder 3)